Guide to the Independent Aid, Inc. Records, 1934-1954
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Independent Aid, Inc. records 1934-1954
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Independent Aid, Inc.
6.4 Linear Feet 314 Items
Independent Aid, Inc. was the first charitable foundation established by Doris Duke, daughter of businessman and philanthropist James Buchanan (J.B.) Duke. It was incorporated in Delaware in October, 1934. Although Miss Duke had limited direct involvement with Independent Aid, its disbursements reflected her persistent interests in the welfare of women and children, education, social work and mental health, and early family planning efforts. The foundation’s daily operations were administered largely by Marian Paschal, who served as Secretary until her death in 1946, and by her successor, Georgea T. Furst. Independent Aid, Inc. became the Doris Duke Foundation in 1951.
The collection spans the years 1934 to 1954, beginning with the establishment of Independent Aid, Inc. and including administrative entries through the first years of the Doris Duke Foundation. Journals, cashbooks, ledgers, and minute books comprise the majority of the collection; these detail contributions to the foundation as well as disbursements. The remaining materials include correspondence, the foundation’s original by-laws, federal tax forms, financial records and lists of stock holdings, and memoranda documenting daily operations.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Independent Aid, Inc. Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a donation from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation in June 2009.
Historical Note
Independent Aid, Inc. was the first charitable foundation established by Doris Duke, daughter of businessman and philanthropist James Buchanan (J.B.) Duke. It was incorporated in Delaware in October, 1934, shortly after Miss Duke turned 21 years of age. The foundation’s daily operations were administered largely by Marian Paschal, who served as Secretary until her death in 1946, and by her successor, Georgea T. Furst. Although Miss Duke had limited direct involvement with Independent Aid, its disbursements reflected her persistent interests in the welfare of women and children, social work and mental health, and early family planning efforts; recipients included the Center for Self-Supporting Women and Students of New York City, the Mental Hygiene Association, and the Child Adoption and Placement Bureau among many others. Additionally, many individuals received funds either to sustain them through financial difficulties or as educational loans and scholarships. In October, 1951, the officers of Independent Aid, Inc. voted to change its name to the Doris Duke Foundation.
Collection Overview
The Independent Aid, Inc. Records (formerly IA.9A) are part of the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation Historical Archives which were donated to the Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library by the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation. The collection covers the operations of Independent Aid, Inc. from its establishment in 1934 through 1951, when it became the Doris Duke Foundation. Fourteen journals, cashbooks, ledgers, and minute books comprise the majority of the collection and detail contributions to the foundation as well as disbursements. One journal, one cashbook, and one ledger extend through 1954. The remaining materials include correspondence, the foundation’s original by-laws, federal tax forms, financial records and lists of stock holdings, and memoranda documenting daily operations. Of particular note are reports made to Marian Paschal, Secretary of Independent Aid, Inc. until her death in 1946, detailing the circumstances of aid recipients and thank you notes to Miss Paschal.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Duke, Doris, 1912-1993
Independent Aid, Inc
Doris Duke Foundation
Doris Duke Charitable Foundation
Charitable foundations
Contents of Collection
- Administrative Records, 1934-1954
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to contributions made by Independent Aid, Inc. File includes thank you notes to Miss Paschal. 1934–1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials concerning the daily operations of Independent Aid, Inc. Materials also include tax bulletins, minutes, and Annual Reports on IA from State of Delaware. 1946–1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cash statements of Independent Aid, Inc. Also includes balance sheets, work sheets, and contributions to organizations. 1935–1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - By-laws, Independent Aid, Inc. 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - List, contributions of Independent Aid, Inc. 1937–1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cashbook, No. 4. 1950–1954 (Oversize-box 2)
  - Journal, No. 4. 1950–1954 (Oversize-box 2)
  - Ledger, No. 4. 1950–1953 (Oversize-box 2)
  - Cashbook, 1934–1939 (Oversize-box 3)
  - Cashbook, No. 2, 1940-May 1945 (Oversize-box 3)
  - Cashbook, No. 3, June 1945-1949 (Oversize-box 3)
  - Journal, 1934-January 1940 (Oversize-box 3)
  - Journal, No. 2, January 1940-June 1945 (Oversize-box 3)
  - Journal, No. 3, June 1945-1949 (Oversize-box 3)
  - Ledger, 1934-1939 (Oversize-box 3)
  - Ledger, No. 2, 1940-May 1945 (Oversize-box 3)
  - Ledger, No. 3, June 1945-1949 (Oversize-box 3)
  - Minutes of the monthly meetings of the Board of Directors of Independent Aid. Includes Certificate of Incorporation, 1934-1941 (1 of 2) (Box 4)
  - Minutes of the monthly meetings of the Board of Directors of Independent Aid. Includes Certificate of Incorporation, 1934-1941 (2 of 2) (Box 4)
  - Minutes of the monthly meetings of the Board of Directors of Independent Aid, 1941-1951 (1 of 2) (Box 5)
  - Minutes of the monthly meetings of the Board of Directors of Independent Aid, 1941-1951 (2 of 2) (Box 5)